Biography Collection, 1771-1995 (bulk 1920s-70s)
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Biography collection
1771-1995
1920-1970
MS 393
17 boxes; 10 volumes (6.25 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
This collection consists of biographical material on both famous and lesser-known women and men. For the most part, there is only a small amount of material on each individual. Materials typically include published and unpublished biographical sketches, books, correspondence, diaries, genealogies, photographs, and published and unpublished writings.
This collection consists of biographical material related to both well-known and unknown women and men whose lives spanned the years from 1771-1970s. Notable individuals represented include Mary McLeod Bethune, Bernard Baruch, Lizzie Borden, Eleanor Butler and Sarah Ponsonby (The Ladies of Llangollen), Tennessee Claflin Cook, Grace Coolidge, Angela Davis, Mary Daly, Hannah Dustin, Dorothy Gish, Julia Ward Howe, Anne Hutchinson, Mother Jones, Helen Keller, Florynce Kennedy, Joan Little, Eleanor Roosevelt, Alice Roosevelt Longworth, Florence Luscomb, Rosa Luxemburg, Marie Antoinette, Margaret Mead, Pauli Murray, Anna Lord Strauss, Rose Pastor Stokes, Annie Sullivan Macy, and Victoria Woodhull.
For the most part, there is only a small amount of material on each individual. Files are organized alphabetically by name. Materials typically include published and unpublished biographical sketches, books, correspondence, diaries, genealogies, newspaper clippings, photographs, and published and unpublished writings. The files of individuals such as Lizzie Borden and Angela Davis also include legal documents. Davis' file (the largest in the collection) also contains memoranda, postcards, political buttons, leaflets, petitions, newsletters, trial bulletins, press releases, and political cartoons which document the movement organized to agitate for a fair trial and freedom for Davis and other political prisoners.
Some lesser-known individuals include interesting and significant material as well, such as Ferdinanda Wesselhoeft's personal letters in German detailing daily life in the United States during the period 1842-1886; the letters and journals of Anna Green Winslow and Mary Hutchinson Parmele dating from the 1770s and 1780s; and correspondence to Ethel Clyde from such famous individuals as Pearl Buck, Albert Einstein, Helen Keller, Pauli Murray, Norman Thomas, Mary van Kleeck, Margaret Sanger, and A.J. Muste. Finally the collection contains a small number of collected biographies including those that document the lives of women associated with Princeton University, White House brides, "women who wanted to be men," and living daughters of presidents.
This collection is organizedas follows:
SERIES I. INDIVIDUALS
SERIES II. COLLECTED BIOGRAPHIES AND BIBLIOGRAPHIES
OVERSIZE MATERIALS
BOOKS ON SHELF
Files arranged alphabetically by name.
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The collection is open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
Additions to the Collection
Periodic additions to collection are expected.
History of the Collection
Materials in this subject collection were either purchased or given to the Sophia Smith Collection by various donors.
Search Terms
Bethune, Mary McLeod, 1875-1955; Baruch, Bernard M. (Bernard Mannes), 1870-1965; Borden, Lizzie, 1860-1927; Butler, Eleanor, Lady, 1738 or 9-1829; Ponsonby, Sarah, 1754 or 5-1831; Coolidge, Grace Goodhue, 1879-1957; Davis, Angela Yvonne, 1944-; Daly, Mary, 1928-; Duston, Hannah Emerson, b. 1657; Gish, Dorothy; Flexner, Eleanor, 1908-; Howe, Julia Ward, 1819-1910; Hutchinson, Anne Marbury, 1591-1643; Jones, Mother, 1843?-1930; Keller, Helen, 1880-1968; Kennedy, Florynce, 1916-; Little, Joan; Longworth, Alice Roosevelt, 1884-1980; Luscomb, Florence, 1887-; Luxemburg, Rosa, 1871-1919; Marie Antoinette, Queen, consort of Louis XVI, King of France, 1755-1793; Mead, Margaret, 1901-1978; Murray, Pauli, 1910-; Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1884-1962; Strauss, Anna Lord, 1899-1979; Stokes, Rose Pastor, 1879-1933; Sullivan, Annie, 1866-1936; Woodhull, Victoria C. (Victoria Claflin), 1838-1927; Buck, Pearl S. (Pearl Sydenstricker), 1892-1973; Sophia Smith Collection
Additional Information
Related Material
Note that many of these individuals are also represented in other collections in the Sophia Smith Collection.
- SERIES I. INDIVIDUALS
  - Adams, Hannah, [see Books on Shelf]
  - Adams, Mary (Newbury): letter to Theo Tilton, 1869 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Andrews, Nellie (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Anthony, Susan B. (Box 1, Folder 2a)
  - Ayers, Agnes (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Baczek, Genevieve (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bailey, Anne (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Barakat, Layyah (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Baruch, Bernard M.: letter to F. B. Sampson (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bary, H. Valeska (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Bedinger, Caroline L. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bellaway, Madge (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Belmont, Margaret Andrews (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Berenson, Mary (Smith) Costelloe (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Bethune, Mary McLeod (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Bettons, Louise, [see also Books on Shelf] (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Bingham, Millicent Todd (Box 1A, Folder 1)
  - Bissell, Emily (Box 1A, Folder 2)
  - Bordon, Lizzie (Box 1A, Folder 3)
  - Borgese, Elizabeth Mann (Box 1A, Folder 4)
  - Breamer, Sylvia (Box 1A, Folder 5)
  - Brent, Evelyn (Box 1A, Folder 6)
  - Brent, Margaret (Box 1A, Folder 7)
  - Brian, Mary (Box 1A, Folder 8)
  - Bronson, Betty (Box 1A, Folder 9)
  - Butler, Lady Eleanor (and Sarah Ponsonby) "Ladies of Llangollen" (Box 1A, Folder 10)
  - Cannon, Annie Wells (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Carroll, Anna Ella, [see Books on Shelf] (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Carter, Mary (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Chace, Elizabeth Buffum (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Chaplin, Charlie (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Clarke, Bertha M. [See next box]
  - Clark, Olive Cleaveland (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Clyde, Ethel [See separate box]
  - Coburn, Helen Galvin Smith: diary from Europe, 1870 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Commander, Lydia Kingsmill (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Cook, Tennessee Claflin, Lady, 1845-1923 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Coolidge, Grace G. to M. G. Smith (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Corey, Esther (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Cotton, Sallie Southall (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Crane, Caroline Bartlett (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Clarke, Bertha M. (Box 2A, Folder 1)
  - Clyde, Ethel, [see also Books on Shelf]
    - Biographical Information (Box 2B, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence (Box 2B, Folder 2)
    - Birth Control (Box 2B, Folder 3)
    - Organizations (Box 2B, Folder 4)
  - Davis, Angela
    - Articles, 1969-70 (Box 2C, Folder 1)
    - Miscellaneous printed material 1970-71, undated (Box 2C, Folder 2)
    - National Committee to Free Angela Davis; Frameup, 1972 (Box 2C, Folder 3)
    - National United Committee to Free Angela Davis: Statements, newsletters, printed material, 1970-71 (Box 2C, Folder 4)
    - New York Committee to Free Angela Davis, 1970-71 (Box 2C, Folder 5)
    - Pamphlets (Box 2C, Folder 6)
    - Political cartoons (Box 2C, Folder 7)
    - Clippings, 1969-76, undated (Box 2D, Folder 1-8)
  - Daly, Mary (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Daniel, Bebe (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - D'Arusmont, Francess Wright (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Daw, Majorie (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Deland, Margaret (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Deloria, Ella C. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Dickey, Sarah A. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Dietrich, Irene E. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Denton, Elizabeth H. Foote (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Drysdale, Robert and Bessie (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Dustan, Hannah (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Ferguson, Miriam ("Ma") (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Fitzgerald, Zelda and Scottie (Box 3, Folder 12aa)
  - Flexner, Eleanor (Box 3, Folder 12a)
  - Fox, Ruth May (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Fransisco, Ethel B. (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Garfield, Eleanor Borton (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Garfield, Lucretia Rudolph (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Gaylord, Katherine (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - George, Zelma Watson (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Gish, Dorothy (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Grant, Fidelia (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Green, Ann Jeanette (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Greenbie, Marjoire Barstow (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Griffin, Coriane (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Gundrada de Warenne (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Harding, Florence Kling, 1860-1925 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Harris, Erna P.: Journalist, political activist, 1986-90 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Holmes, Julia Archibald (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Hooker, Isabella Beecher (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Howe, Julia Ward (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Hutchinson, Anne (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Hyman, Libbie Henrietta (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Ingersoll, Marion Crary (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Inglis, Agnes Anne (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Jarvis, Anna Bailey (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Jekyll, Gertrude (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Jones, Mary Harris (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Karsten, Eleannor Daggett (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Kasson, Maria (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Kato, Shidzue (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Kaufman, Shirley (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Kayden, Sandra (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Keller, Helen (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Kennedy, Florynce (Box 4A, Folder 1)
  - Knowlton, Charles (Box 4A, Folder 2)
  - La Marr, Barbara (Box 4A, Folder 3)
  - Laughlin, Gail (Box 4A, Folder 4)
  - Lee, Lela (Box 4A, Folder 5)
  - Leiser, Clara (Box 4A, Folder 6)
  - Little, Joan (Box 4A, Folder 7)
  - Livermore, Mary Ashton Rice (Box 4A, Folder 8)
  - Longworth, Alice (Roosevelt) (Box 4A, Folder 9)
  - Lord-Heinstein, Lucile (Box 4A, Folder 10)
  - Lowell, Josephine Shaw, [see Books on Shelf]
  - Lumbard, Elizabeth T. (Box 4A, Folder 11)
  - Luscomb, Florence H. (Box 4A, Folder 12)
  - Luxemburg, Rosa (Box 4A, Folder 13)
  - Lyon, Ben (Box 4A, Folder 14)
  - McAvoy, May (Box 4A, Folder 15)
  - Marie Antoinette, Queen Consort of Louis XVI (Box 4A, Folder 16)
  - Marion, Kitty (Box 4A, Folder 17)
  - Mead, Lucia Ames (Box 4A, Folder 18)
  - Mead, Margaret (Box 4A, Folder 19)
  - Mills, Harriet May (Box 4A, Folder 20)
  - Milton, Mary Powell (Box 4A, Folder 21)
  - Morgan, Agnes (Box 4A, Folder 22)
  - Montagu, Elizabeth (Box 4A, Folder 23)
  - Moore, Sarah: poem and lock of hair, 1841 (Box 4A, Folder 24)
  - Murray, Mae (Box 4A, Folder 25)
  - Murray, Pauli (Box 4A, Folder 26)
  - Myers, Carmel (Box 4A, Folder 27)
  - Nation, Carry Amelia (Moore) (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Nickerson, Edith Child, [See Books on Shelf]
  - Norrie, Margaret (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Parmele, Mary Hutchinson: Journal (unpublished), 1782-84 [see also note in finding aid file] (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Patten, Ruth, [see Books on Shelf]
  - Pickford, Mary (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Pinkham, Lydia Estes (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Pollard, Marie Antoinette (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Posner, Henriette
    - Correspondence from her, 1934 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence to her from John Haynes Holmes 1933-56 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence to her from Orlo Price, 1933; David Phys Williams, 1953-54; and Barbara Young, 1933 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Prevost, Marie (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Pringle, Aileen (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Pringle, Julia (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Ralston, Esther (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Rama Rau, Dhanvanthi [see separate box]
  - Rhoudda, Viscountess (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Ripley, Mrs. (Samuel), [See Books on Shelf]
  - Robinson, Helen Josephy (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Roland, Ruth (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Roosevelt, Edith Kermit (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Roosevelt, Eleanor [see separate box]
  - Rama Rau, Dhanvanthi: An Inheritance (manuscript) (Box 5A)
  - Roosevelt, Eleanor: correspondence, reports, articles, books, pamphlets, 1924-73 [unprocessed --see separate list] (Box 5b)
  - Russell, E.S., [See Books on Shelf]
  - Salmon, Lucy Maynard (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Sanville, Florence (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Sayre, Ruth Buxton (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Scattergood, Margaret (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Scranton, Katherine M. Smith (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Skeffington, Hanna Sheehy (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Silkwood, Karen (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Slocum, Frances, [See Books on Shelf]
  - Smith, Amy Grinnell (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Smith, Lydia A. (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Smith, Mary Byers (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Strauss, Anna Lord (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Stokes, Rose Pastor (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Sullivan, (Macy) Anne (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Sumter, Natalie, [See Books on Shelf]
  - Swanson, Gloria (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Sweet, Blanche (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Talmadye, Constance (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Tappan, Sarah, [See Books on Shelf]
  - Thoburn, Isabella (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Thompson, Betty (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Vickery, Alice (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Votey, Constance (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Warren, Cornelia (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Webster, Elizabeth H. (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Wesselhoeft, Ferdinanda Emilie (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Whitton Collection (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Willard, Harriet Jane (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Williams, Fannie Barrier (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Willmarth, Mary Howes (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Wills, Frances (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Wilson, Elizabeth Millar (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Wilson, Lois (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Winslow, Anna Green (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Windsor, Wallis Warfield (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Woodhull, Victoria Clafin, [See also Books on Shelf]
    - General (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - "Humanitarian Money: The Unsolved Riddle," by Victoria Woodhull, 1892 (Box 7, Folder 18b)
  - Yaggy, Laura Reed, [See Oversize material]
- SERIES II. COLLECTED BIOGRAPHIES AND BIBLIOGRAPHIES
  - Collected biographies (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Collected biographies: clippings (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Living daughters of U.S. Presidents, 1967 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Bibliographies (Box 8, Folder 4)
- OVERSIZE MATERIALS
  - Yaggy, Laura Reed: photocopies of biographical sketch, photographs, correspondence and clippings (spiral bound), circa 1901-84 (Box 9)
  - Victoria Woodhull: Champion of Humanity, May 2 and 16, 1874 (Map-case Flat File)
- BOOKS ON SHELF, [Note: additional published biographies are in the Browsing collection in SSC/CA Reading Room and the Staff Library-listed in card catalog]
  - A Memoir of Miss Hannah Adams, Hannah Adams, 1832
  - Mrs. Louise E. Bettons, undated
  - A Military Genius: Life of Anna Ella Carrol, Sarah Ellen Blackwell, 1891
  - A Review of Pierce's Administration, Anna Ella Carroll, 1856
  - The Union of the States, Anna Ella Carroll, 1856
  - Horse Sense, Ethel Clyde (2 copies), 1969
  - What About You?, Theodore Schroeder, edited with introduction by Ethel Clyde, 1951
  - Rachel Dumont; A Brave Little Maid Revolution, Mary Westbrook, 1884
  - The Philanthropic Work of Josephine Shaw Lowell, William R. Stewart, 1911
  - Once Upon a Time and To-day, Mand Nathan, 1933
  - Grace and Remembrance: My Grandmother Edith Child Nickerson, Nancy Child Perry, 1981
  - Memoirs of Mrs. Ruth Patten, William Patten, 1834
  - Mrs. Samuel Ripley, R.W. Emerson, 1877
  - Seasons of a Woman's Life, Alice S. Rossi, 1983
  - The Ever-Widening Circle, E.S. Russell, 1983
  - Frances Slocum of Miami Lodge, Joseph Allen Minturn, 1928
  - The Transatlantic Smiths, Robert Allerton Parker
  - Fifteen Letters of Nathalie Sumter, introduction and notations by Mary Virginia Saunders White, 1942
  - Memoirs of Mrs. Sarah Tappan, 1834
  - Love and Money: Grandmothers' Strategies with Spouses and Bosses, edited by Terisa E. Turner (Umass Amherst Women's Studies Dept.), 1990
  - The Queens of American Society, Mrs. Ellet, 1887
  - American Lady of the Manor, Bredon's Norton: The Later Life of Victoria Woodhull Martin, 1901-1927, Owen Stinchcombe, 2000
  - The Human Body the Temple of God: or, The Philosophy of Sociology, by Victoria Claflin Woodhull (Mrs. John Biddulph Martin) and Tennessee C. Claflin (Lady Cook), 1890